<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-03-23T13:47:01-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Cruft City Express</title><subtitle>⚙ ⚙ ⚙</subtitle><entry><title type="html">AE-1 and the Mystery Lenses</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/AE-1_strange_lenses/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AE-1 and the Mystery Lenses" /><published>2021-02-20T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-02-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/AE-1_strange_lenses</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/AE-1_strange_lenses/">&lt;p&gt;We had some strange old lenses in our attic and I was excited to try them out on the AE-1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ae-1_mystery_lenses/funny_lenses.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are from left to right:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kern-Paillard Switar 25mm&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kern-Paillard Yvar 75mm&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cosmicar 8.5mm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kern-Paillar started making camera lenses in 1914 and stopped making the Switar and Yvar in the 1950s. These lenses appear to be on the newer side, but still getting up there in age. So far, Eleanor has managed to make the Yvar produced some good photos. I took a couple with the Switar but haven’t gotten them developed yet. The Cosmicar has proved to be somewhat challenging so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the lenses above are &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C_mount&quot;&gt;C mount&lt;/a&gt; lenses. This lens mount was developed way back in the day, Wikipedia estimates its first used to have been in 1926. The AE-1 is an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canon_FD_lens_mount&quot;&gt;FD mount&lt;/a&gt; camera, so an adapter would be needed. Of course, there are no C mount lens to FD camera adapters (there are adapters that go the other way) and I can’t get into MITERS because of COVID. So this was going to be a franken-adapter situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After much googling, the adapter stackup that did the trick was an FD body to M42, then an M42 body to C mount. The M42 threads were incredibly loose, so some thread locker was needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the Switar with the adapter:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ae-1_mystery_lenses/disassembled.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ae-1_mystery_lenses/assembled.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are a couple of the pictures Eleanor took with Portra 400 film and the Kern-Paillard Yvar 75mm lens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ae-1_mystery_lenses/000052250016.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ae-1_mystery_lenses/000052250017.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">We had some strange old lenses in our attic and I was excited to try them out on the AE-1.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/ae-1_mystery_lenses/funny_lenses.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/ae-1_mystery_lenses/funny_lenses.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">AE-1 Repair</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/AE-1_repair/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AE-1 Repair" /><published>2021-01-16T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-01-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/AE-1_repair</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/AE-1_repair/">&lt;p&gt;Right at the beginning of the pandemic, Theo gave me this &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canon_AE-1&quot;&gt;Canon AE-1&lt;/a&gt; with a really nice Tamron Adaptall 35-80mm lens and a stuck shutter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ae-1_repair/hero.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After removing the bottom panel, the shutter could be mechanically released by pushing the small trapezoidal magnet (under the clear plastic cover) away from the electromagnet. This meant that the camera was mechanically sound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ae-1_repair/bottom.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the next place to look was at the shutter electronics which are all on the gold flex pcb to the left of the electromagnet. After undoing the bolt constraining the flex and freeing the electromagnet from its housing, it was clear that something was missing. A component had fallen off the board. Just below the resistor in the following picture you can see the two well-aged leads of a through-hole component conspicuously disconnected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ae-1_repair/missing_diode.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The repair manual informed me that this was supposed to be a diode, so I bought one and soldered it on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ae-1_repair/fresh_diode.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The repair manual is surprisingly well written and relatively comprehensive. It includes the following diagram of the shutter electronics which shows that the diode is used to charge up capacitor c47. The capacitor can then be discharged through the windings of Mg2, pushing the shutter magnet away from the coils. The lack of diode had been preventing the cap from charging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ae-1_repair/shutter_circuit_diagram.png&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even with the fresh diode in place, the shutter electronics still failed to release when the trigger was pressed. After probing a couple of the components on the flex, I found a that the windings around the magnet Mg2 had broken. I desoldered the magnet and hoped that the break wasn’t somewhere deep in the coil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ae-1_repair/magnet_fixed.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, after some searching the break was visible. Soldering the magnet wire took a few tries. It is hair thin and coated in enamel to prevent shorts. The internet suggested burning the enamel off with a lighter, but the wire was so thin that it burned just as quickly as the enamel did. The eventual solution was to pass a hot soldering iron across the wire a few times to remove the enamel. The solder joint is at the upper left of the coil in the image above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the coils conducting and the magnet back in place, the shutter finally fired. When I put the bottom cover back on the camera, the shutter stopped firing. After some searching, it turns out that the leads on my new diode were a little bit too long and the bottom cover was causing them to short to the camera body. After trimming the stray leads, the camera was ready to take some pictures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/dDPwm8bHLXM&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are a couple of the pictures Eleanor took with Portra 400 film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ae-1_repair/000024660009.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ae-1_repair/000024660016.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ae-1_repair/000024660031.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ae-1_repair/000024660019.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Right at the beginning of the pandemic, Theo gave me this Canon AE-1 with a really nice Tamron Adaptall 35-80mm lens and a stuck shutter.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/ae-1_repair/hero.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/ae-1_repair/hero.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>